<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Marcin Gliński</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/</id><updated>2016-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>New Beginning­ ­— Melted Vertex Games</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2016-01/new-beginning-melted-vertex-games.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Marcin Gliński</name></author><id>tag:blog.marcinglinski.pl,2016-01-01:2016-01/new-beginning-melted-vertex-games.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;January is a funny month. Gyms and swimming pools all over the world record increased 
gainings. Side walks are full of wannabe runners and tabaco industry records decline
in profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've decided to join the New Year's train and start something new. There are stories
that happen to start with "Once upon a time". There a stories that begins with "So, you wanna hear
another story, eh?". My story starts with...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The logo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Melted Vertex Games logo" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0009-logo.png" /&gt;
&lt;em class="center-block text-center"&gt;Melted Vertex Games logo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This single person hobby project called "Melted Vertex Games" with a bit of luck and dozen
of determination will hopefully create new chapter in my life. You know how they say,
"Start small, dream big". And that's what I'm going to do.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="mvg"></category><category term="art"></category></entry><entry><title>LD33: Ghosty Game post mortem</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2015-09/ld33-ghosty-game-post-mortem.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Marcin Gliński</name></author><id>tag:blog.marcinglinski.pl,2015-09-19:2015-09/ld33-ghosty-game-post-mortem.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Results of Ludum Dare 33 got already published so it's time for postmortem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main goal — making the game in time for the &lt;em&gt;Compo&lt;/em&gt; — has not been acomplished.
I was far from having anything ready to be send and the deadline has been reached.
After getting some sleep, rest and spending time with family I decided not to
give up completely and try to drive the game to the finish line called &lt;em&gt;Jam&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For these readers who have no clue what's the difference between &lt;abbr title="Ludum Dare"&gt;LD&lt;/abbr&gt; Compo and Jam, 
in short:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time to post entry to the compo is 48h, while for Jam it's 72h&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are only allowed to work solo in the Compo, but for Jam you might work in a 
  team made of programmers, gfx artists, musicans, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For Compo you must create all in–game assets (graphics, audio) by yourself and 
  all of these need to be made during the 48h of the Compo. For Jam you are
  allowed to use already existing assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compo is very strict and limiting, while Jam is more careless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;    ​ 
​

  .---------------.-----------------.-----------------.
  |               |      LD 30      |       LD 33     |
  |  Category     |                 |                 |
  |               |  Score |  Place |  Score |  Place |
  +---------------+------- +--------+--------+--------+
  | Overall       |  2.79  |   950  |  3.00  |   716  |
  | Audio         |  2.19  |   816  |  2.41  |   623  |      Good job, minion!
  | Fun           |  2.85  |   730  |  3.11  |   485  |
  | Graphics      |  2.85  |   727  |  2.94  |   734  |           ,
  | Humor         |  2.67  |   354  |  ----  |   ---  |           |
  | Innovation    |  2.44  |  1022  |  2.53  |   873  |        ]  |.-._
  | Mood          |  2.75  |   766  |  ----  |   ---  |         \|&amp;quot;(0)&amp;quot;| _]
  | Theme         |  2.33  |  1056  |  2.31  |  1049  |         `|=\#/=|\/
  `---------------&amp;#39;--------&amp;#39;--------&amp;#39;--------&amp;#39;--------&amp;#39;          :  _  :
                                                                  \/_\/
                                                                   |=|
                                                                   `-&amp;#39; fsc

    ​ 
    ​
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The results are generally better. Keep also in mind that in &lt;abbr title="Ludum Dare"&gt;LD&lt;/abbr&gt; Jam you compete
against teams of people, not the lone designers; it's much harder to get better
score due to this single fact. I was really suprised that my overall score is
that high as the game was far from being finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the other hand, I've been slowly working on enhancing my graphics and audio
skills and it seems like some progress has been made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Timelapse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8HihdhlJQYA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What went right&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals were described in the &lt;a href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2015-08/ld33-im-in-for-the-2nd-time.html"&gt;introduction article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Visuals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm really happy that my pixel–art skills got improved. I was able to create
some animations and (for a beginner) decent looking characters. However, there is
still much more room for improvements. My next goal is to have enough skills
to produce content of similar quality to the &lt;a href="http://oryxdesignlab.com/ultimatefantasy"&gt;Ultimate Fantasy tileset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Working on the assets" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0007-pyxel.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;em class="center-block text-center"&gt;Working on the assets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Audio&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music. I've finally made it! The tool of use was Bosca Ceoil. I was using it for
the first time. Bosca Ceoil is an awesome tool to create simple tunes using tons 
of different samples. I think it's good idea to stick to this program for a now
and focus on something else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bosca Ceoil music editor" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0006-music.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;em class="center-block text-center"&gt;Bosca Ceoil music editor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Entity Component System&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the &lt;abbr title="Ludum Dare"&gt;LD&lt;/abbr&gt; I was working on my custom engine, based on &lt;abbr title="Entity Component System"&gt;ECS&lt;/abbr&gt; architecture.
I had no actual game to test if it works properly, so &lt;abbr title="Ludum Dare"&gt;LD&lt;/abbr&gt; was a first test.
There were nasty bugs that took some time from my developement, mostly related
to initialization as I was reusing preallocated memory for component data,
but overall I'm really happy with the architecture. If you start thinking
with components and not game objects, everything magically starts working.
If you got your rendering, physics and audio systems already prepared you 
might focus on actual gameplay because attaching proper components will 
make everything magically work! This is the reason why people use engines
like Unity. Few hours later you got working prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What went wrong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Deadline missed&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was unable to deliver in time an entry for compo. I've lost over 6 hours of 
development due to a basic indexing issue which shouldn't happen to any 
software engineer. I didn't have any physic system ready to be used so I had
to make one by myself. This combined with not tested &lt;abbr title="Entity Component System"&gt;ECS&lt;/abbr&gt;–engine resulted
in too much time spent in a debugger trying to figure out what's going on.
Lesson (I hope) learnt and (I hope) next time I'll focus more on actual
gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lack of actual gameplay&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big loss. As I've lost too much time fighting windmills, 
only single planned gameplay feature has been implemented. My plan was to
create a stealth evasion game with static obstacles, moving enemies with 
their cone of view, sound alarm system, bullet hell and simple logic 
puzzles (push this button to activate that). To me this game is far from
being playable. No idea where the 3.0 overall rating came from, but it's
kind of intresting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lesson to learn&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just one lesson but the most important one: &lt;strong&gt;be focused on all the 
little things&lt;/strong&gt; in a software development process…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… such as table indices or early function exits, as they may screw your
mind when you try to debug complex logics. If you name variables, even
for side projects such as &lt;abbr title="Ludum Dare"&gt;LD&lt;/abbr&gt; entries, use good naming convention.
I've spend over 6h because I couldn't find the mistake in 2d → 1d array 
index conversion; I've used wrong variable to determine size of the 
row (tile's width in pixels instead of number of tiles in
a row). It could have been avoided if I hadn't had variables named &lt;code&gt;TW&lt;/code&gt;
(Tile Width) and &lt;code&gt;WW&lt;/code&gt; (World Width). When participating in &lt;abbr title="Ludum Dare"&gt;LD&lt;/abbr&gt;, you 
should have proffesional mindset too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Index bug when setting up VertexArray" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0008-indexbug.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;em class="center-block text-center"&gt;Debugging index bug described above&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second bug, that cost me some time, was a removal of early function
exit when calculating a direction from velocity vector. Due to 
refactoring I removed early exit on a vector length check. It resulted
in division by 0, which for floats results in NaN, which resulted in 
wrong position of the player's character, which resulted in a camera 
moved to strange position, which resulted in a whole game state layer not
being drawn and since I was using state-stack design, the MainMenu state got drawn,
which resulted in lost hours in a debugger trying to figure out what
the heck just happened. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other lesson from this bug is: &lt;strong&gt;use asserts whenever you can&lt;/strong&gt;.
For release mode they will be removed. Which leads to the third bug:
putting logic in a preprocessor macro which happen to be removed (changed
to &lt;code&gt;do {} while(0)&lt;/code&gt;) in the release mode. My only explanation is a tiredness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Plans for the future&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next Ludum Dare in 3 months so there's plenty of time for
self–development and engine improvements. Right now I'm trying to
make my new game project to get off the ground. As for the programming 
tasks, I've made the list of things to be done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add more features to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/silentlamb/mve-engine"&gt;mve-engine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cinematics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaders and processing effects (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input rebinding (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic audio system (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare level parser to be used&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parse image (png) based maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parse PyxelEdit txt format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parse Tiled map format (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement algorithm to reduce unnecessary number of rigid bodies when loading a map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare for LD34 (12-14 Dec, 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue improving on pixel arts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="post-mortem"></category><category term="ludum-dare"></category></entry><entry><title>Introduction to the blog</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2015-09/introduction-to-the-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Marcin Gliński</name></author><id>tag:blog.marcinglinski.pl,2015-09-12:2015-09/introduction-to-the-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The blog is finally setup and running. Under the hood the software I use
is &lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; to generate static HTML files from articles written in
Markdown/RST format. Everything is hosted as a &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com"&gt;Github pages feature&lt;/a&gt;
configured to support my custom domain. Time for introduction!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Who am I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the header states my name is Marcin Gliński. I'm a software engineer
working in a mobile company in projects related to Android and audio
processing. The topics related to my work probably won't show up much
often here as I'm not sure how far can I go with NDA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my non-professional time I learn and discover various fields of game
design and development.  Currently I am in the middle of preparing a
toy-engine, written mostly for learning purposes, to be open sourced.
If the time is right I participate in &lt;a href="http://ludumdare.com/compo/rules/"&gt;Ludum Dare competition&lt;/a&gt;.
Having a hard limit of 48h (or 72, depending on the event) to create
game from scratch, is a very challenging task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ghosty game - work in progress" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Topics of this blog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main topics of this blog are engine and game development. My pet
project is a game with top-down perspective mixing various games into
the one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engine itself is written in C++ using SFML library as a OpenGL and
system wrapper. For physics system I've chosen Box2D as it's simple
enough to work with. For a scripting language I use Lua. These
technologies will be shown in my articles for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I don't do any gamedev, I play some indie games. My favourite
genres are roguelikes, top down shooters and platformers. If I find
anything intresting, reviews will be added here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reason to write&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no progress without training. The main reason is to improve my english
writting skills. Creating doxygen/code documentation (especially when you work
with people from Asia) is one thing as you need to write as simple as possible
to be easily understood. Passing your thoughts into a web article is something
completely different. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What else to find here&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous blog under this domain was made to group my ASCII-arts in a single
place.  I don't want them to disappear in the vastness of web archives as they
are part of me.  Altough I don't draw them anymore as my current interests are
pixel and low poly arts, the amount of arts that I created is kind of big and I
want them to be here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;                                    / _,
                               ,_  M\M&amp;quot;_,,
                                `&amp;quot;MMMMMm._
                               `/MMMMMMP^^&amp;quot;,
                                MPTMMM`M    `-.
                              .&amp;#39;&amp;quot;  MMMm  &amp;quot;=, `.`&amp;quot;-.
                            .&amp;#39;  / S _&amp;quot;^M :Ww.  \   `-.
                         .-&amp;#39;  .: &amp;quot;.wW\.; :WP^;  `-.   `-.
                      .-&amp;#39;  .-&amp;#39;/ \ :^WP: ; `--&amp;#39; ;\  `-.   `.
                   .-&amp;#39;  .-&amp;#39;  /  /; `..&amp;#39;  ;      \`.   `-.  \
                  /  .-&amp;#39;   .&amp;#39;  /  ;    .-&amp;quot;;`&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;--5..`-.  `-.\
                 / .&amp;#39;   .-&amp;#39;   /   |  .&amp;#39;    ;       r`) `-.  \\
                ; /  .-&amp;#39;   .-&amp;#39;    ;_/       ;   _   ;     `. \;
                |&amp;#39; .&amp;#39;    .&amp;#39;      ( _    _    : `-&amp;#39;  :\      `./
                `-&amp;#39;     /    .-r-.`Y   `-&amp;#39;   :     /  ;
                       ; .-7&amp;quot;   `.`7.        |   .&amp;#39;   |
                       :  &amp;#39;      ; ; `--..__.&amp;#39;-&amp;quot;&amp;quot;/    ;\
                        \  ,|    | |     ..--&amp;quot;,-&amp;#39;     : ;
             _     _.7`,_J- ;    : ;,      _,&amp;#39;:      /; ;           _
           .&amp;#39; `--.`-.`-&amp;#39;_.-| `.  |/ :    .&amp;#39;/ :      ; | |`&amp;quot;.    _.-&amp;quot;.+.
           :`&amp;quot;-.  `--`&amp;quot;&amp;quot; ,_:   `&amp;#39;7 /.-.   ;  |     /  | :   7&amp;quot;,&amp;#39; .&amp;quot;   |
           :    \       :   `-. / ;&amp;#39;  /   |  |  `--\  /4   &amp;#39;    /  .&amp;#39; ;
           `.    ;      \      :`&amp;quot;\ .&amp;lt;    ;  :   _.7 &amp;#39;  `.     /   /.&amp;#39;
             \   `.___.-&amp;quot;&amp;gt;      ;_/   :---&amp;quot;\ `. &amp;#39;   `.-.. `&amp;quot;--&amp;#39;    /
              `.___..--&amp;quot;/     _mMMMm,.&amp;#39;     `-.`-.._  )  `&amp;quot;--.   .&amp;#39;
                       `---&amp;#39;&amp;quot;mMMMMMMMMm,_      `-----&amp;#39;        `&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
                            `&amp;quot; &amp;quot;^`^MMMP^^mm,
                                                          fsc
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>LD33: Day 1</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2015-08/ld33-day-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Marcin Gliński</name></author><id>tag:blog.marcinglinski.pl,2015-08-22:2015-08/ld33-day-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article is an imported post from Ludum Dare website. I've posted it
at the day 1 of LD33 event. It's added here so I can keep everything related
to a gamedev in a single place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Day 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello Ludum Dare-ers! I hope you're enjoying both compo and the theme. Day&amp;nbsp;1 is
almost done so let me summarize my work today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finished&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testing custom engine for the first time; not working perfectly, but not as
  bad as the last time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main character animations and some static assets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration with Box2D. Tons of stupid issues to resolve. Good lesson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loading level from .png files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TODO for Day 2&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enemies: path finding, very simple AI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More gfx/sfx assets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rendering optimizations and fixes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Juicing the game up (screen shakes, explosions!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design more levels and simple plot structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come up with the title...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure what's going to be dropped. I guess it's the music and more polished
assets again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay after day 1" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0005-day1.gif" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="imported"></category><category term="ludum-dare"></category></entry><entry><title>LD33: I’m in for the 2nd time</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2015-08/ld33-im-in-for-the-2nd-time.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Marcin Gliński</name></author><id>tag:blog.marcinglinski.pl,2015-08-06:2015-08/ld33-im-in-for-the-2nd-time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article is an imported post from Ludum Dare website. I've posted it
at the day 1 of LD30. It's added here so I can keep everything related to
a gamedev in a single place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;I'm in for the 2nd time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello fellow gamedevs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first time (LD30) was a great experience and I really wanted to participate
again. And I’ve got opportunity to join this time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goals for this LD are quite similar to the &lt;a href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2014-08/ld30-node54-final-thoughts.html"&gt;previous ones&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finish a playable game&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s everyone’s main goal, so not much to say.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This time I want to &lt;strong&gt;focus on introducing concept of the game&lt;/strong&gt; to the player,
  so he or she won’t get lost. Last time it was a total failure. Players didn’t
  know what was the goal of the game, nor how to control the avatar, nor what are
  rules to the game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep visual simple, but of decent quality&lt;/strong&gt;. If the topic is right I might
  even try to use a really simple shapes (circles and rectangles). The main
  focus is going to be on a good mix of colors, and little things like gradients
  and shadows. Last time I spent too much time creating unused animation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More fx sounds&lt;/strong&gt;. Sound is a great tool for the feedback and to make the game
  feel alive. I hope I won’t mess the API this time and use the valid volume
  ranges (0-100 instead of 0-1). My tool of use: probably sfxer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music&lt;/strong&gt;. Any music. I’m not a musican at all, but since the beginning of this
  year I’ve been working in the audio/DSP related project. If it’s possible
  I’ll borrow MIDI keyboard from my company for the weekend to motivate me. The
  tool of use is going to be Milky Tracker, unless I find something easy to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have no idea what theme is going to win, but if possible I’m gonna try to
  &lt;strong&gt;make something fast-paced&lt;/strong&gt;. Last time I tried to make clone of “Ugh!” game.
  This time again I’m gonna stick to already explored concepts. It’s still to
  early to me to create anything original, I’d rather focus my work in other
  fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll stick to the tools I know well, so once again game is going to be done in
C++11 and SFML with Box2D or Lua, depending on the theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish you all good luck at the LD33!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="imported"></category><category term="ludum-dare"></category></entry><entry><title>LD30: Node54 - final thoughts</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2014-08/ld30-node54-final-thoughts.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Marcin Gliński</name></author><id>tag:blog.marcinglinski.pl,2014-08-30:2014-08/ld30-node54-final-thoughts.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article is an imported post from Ludum Dare website. I've posted it
as a post mortem of my LD30 entry. It's added here so I can keep everything 
related to a gamedev in a single place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Node54 - final thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2014-08/ld30-lets-meet-node54.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; published during competition, I've described my background
and reasons to participate in Ludum Dare. This time I'd like to talk about
conclusions that came to my mind after finishing LD30 entry and receiving
feedback from various people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;My goals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish a game. This could be the single goal because this is the main reason 
  I've joined LD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The game should be simple enough so it might be done by someone having no 
  experience in gamedev. This means I wanted to use existing idea because
  having no experience in gamedev means I won't be able to finish the game if I
  tried to do something too original.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The game should not have "raw" visuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The game should have some kind of audio: sounds of sfxer + a simple music in
  the background&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The game should be fast-paced and the goal for player is to finish it as fast
  as he/she can&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The game should be looking polished; it should have bindable keys, and
  reasonable amount of juicyness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The game should have possibility to be improved when LD30 is finished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Node54 with an example level" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0003-level.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What went right&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;I've finished playable game&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't sure I was good enough to actually finish a game. I've tried thousands
of times but every time it stopped being a game engine instead of actual game.
Node54 is real and I'm very happy and proud of myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;The game doesn't crash&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it works, it works. It doesn't look to have much bugs expect the collision
issues and sticking to walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Visuals&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is not a kind of beauty, but it also doesn't look bad. My goal of
having not ugly visuals has been fulfilled. Friends told me that the game
background with irregular squares looks really nice when compared to ideal
squares of walls. The best thing is that I've made it for about 4-5 minutes.
Gimp -&amp;gt; pick blue color -&amp;gt; create clouds from filters -&amp;gt; motion blur -&amp;gt; create
mosaic from filters. That's all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Experience&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still want to improve it, I got plenty of ideas so further development will
be continued for sure. Now that I have already a playable it's gonna be much
easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've learned a lot. I've improved some technical skills as well as mental ones.
Finishing this game gave me enormous amount of confidence and motivation. I've
learned the importance of having 10-30 minutes long breaks from a work. Proper
amount of sleep is also substantial. The best thing about our brain is that
when we sleep it doesn't fully shutdown. It's resting in a standby mode in
which it dumps a lot of garbage thoughts. When you wake up (after morning
coffee of course) it contains with thousands of ideas what to do next and how
to do it. If I wasn't sleeping for at least 6 hours every day, me rate of work
would be significantly slower. I also wanted to to let it go on the second day.
My code was so much of garbage that I couldn't implement anything I wanted. So
i thought to myself: time for a shower and some hot beverage. It helped. I
refactored few critical "god" classes and everything started to work as I
wanted it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Linux port&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux port which I haven't planned. The good thing about using a wrapper lib
like SFML is that porting is very simple. The code is almost not touched
(almost), and the only thing you need to resolve is compilation and linking to
be finished successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What went wrong&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Time management&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't quite aware of how little time I was given. My first idea for the
development of Node54 was to implement physics (movement + collisions) by
myself. By the end of day one I was having movement of poor quality and no
collision at all. When I was thinking on the collision module design I realized
that it's going be very, very thought to finish. So many edge cases, so many
debugging. And then I read in some social media post that this guy has
something playable thanks to Box2D. I heard about this library but that's all.
So I've decided to give it a try. Manual was kind of well-written, so I've
managed to finish collision system. What went wrong? I was learning Box2D from
scratch and due to no experience I wasn't aware of several issues. First of
all, visual debugging. If I could prepare it before LD it would be much easier
to resolve issues related to pixels-&amp;gt;meters conversions and not updating
Box2D/SFML positions. Next thing are issues with friction. Walls in Node54 are
simple rectangles. This means that friction attached to them is the same
horizontally and vertically. Because of that player sometimes stick to walls.
If I divided every block to 4 triangles I could set different friction to
different part of the wall block. Another thing is collision box of the player.
I've used simple rectangle because I wanted to replace this temporary drawn
blue guy with something better. The idea was to add a frame to look more like a
moving platform. I didn't have enough time to have it done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Temporary visuals&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a saying in software development, that temporary solutions are the
most persistent. I really wanted to make it more pixelarty, unfortunately my
pixel art skills requires quite a long piece of time which I could not afford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Quality of audio&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only sounds I've added to the game were simple samples generated by sfxer.
Unfortunately I haven't read the documentation carefully, so instead setting
volume within the range of (0.f - 100.f) I used (0.f - 1.f).  This means that
sound cannot be heard. I wanted to create some chip tune music in Milky Tracker
but again: no time and no skills to make it fast. I definitely want to improve
that in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Lack of feedback&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No guide for a player what the game is about and how to play it. For me it was
obvious that I move using arrow keys and when you want to move up you need to
push yourself from the ground. It was also obvious that when player is given
too much of speed it's going to crash during contact with walls. Player don't
receive any feedback and is not given any guide of the rules. He doesn't know
that he has to pick cargo boxes of a color and deliver it to the flag of same
color. He doesn't know that to pick a cargo he needs to press spacebar key. He
doesn't know that when you pick a cargo it cannot be dropped until delivered. A
lot of little things so obvious to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Lack of juiciness&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No juiciness in game. No animations. I've skipped animation part because I
thought that it's going to take too much development time from me. So
everything is static. In my engine I don't even have a class for animations. I
started to drawing some animations (explosion which is present in the assets
folder) but it only took some time and didn't make it to the final game. There
is no screen shake when player dies. There are no particles when the player
starts moving. This little things that make every game look polished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tilesets from the game" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0004-atlas.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What next?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LD30 entry is finished so now it's plenty of time to resolve every issues and
implement every feature I wanted. To make this game look the way I want it to
look. I'm going to start a project devlog thread on TigSource forums if you are
interested. If you want to give the game a try, here's the &lt;a href="http://ludumdare.com/compo/ludum-dare-30/?action=preview&amp;amp;uid=40102"&gt;entry page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;edit [2015-09-19]&lt;/em&gt;: After few minor improvements (audio and visual 
alarm when player's speed is too high, fixed sticking to walls bug) the
project got dumped in order to work on different things.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="imported"></category><category term="ludum-dare"></category><category term="post-mortem"></category></entry><entry><title>LD30: Let's meet Node54</title><link href="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/2014-08/ld30-lets-meet-node54.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Marcin Gliński</name></author><id>tag:blog.marcinglinski.pl,2014-08-23:2014-08/ld30-lets-meet-node54.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article is an imported post from Ludum Dare website. I've posted it
at the day 1 of LD30. It's added here so I can keep everything related to
a gamedev in a single place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Let's meet Node54&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;skipped introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I love game development. I read tons of stuff. I try to think about
various algorithms or design patterns that might be used to resolve some
problem that bugs me. The problem is, I haven't finish anything yet. All
of my game development stops on the engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So one day, looking at the calendar I saw that my wife with son are
going out and they won't be at home for the whole weekend. And the great
thing about it is that the same weekend belongs to LD30! So I thought to
myself: why not try to sign in? And here I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Main screen of Node54" class="img-thumbnail center-block" src="http://blog.marcinglinski.pl/images/0002-title.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after 10h of design and development (Inkscape, GIMP, PyxelEdit, VS
C++ &amp;amp; SFML lib) I've achieved the following state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple rendering engine using stack states is done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resources management (textures, fonts) is finished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Level loader that uses .png files as its input is finished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Level mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple assets are finished: menu background, game background and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still to be done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collision detection, this is main mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Player movement based on gravity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio effects &amp;amp; Music (there's gonna be no music probably as I don't 
  know much about this topic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sprite polishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better input handling: Joystick support + rebindable keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe (big maybe) PCG-ed levels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="imported"></category><category term="ludum-dare"></category></entry></feed>